<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Simon Research Ensemble</title><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on The Simon Research Ensemble</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://simonensemble.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>what's the distribution of a random variable after a nonlinear transformation?</title><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2022-03-13-transformation-rv/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2022-03-13-transformation-rv/</guid><description/></item><item><title>earth mover's distance</title><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2022-02-12-emd/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2022-02-12-emd/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Surviving the bridge in Squid Game (Chalkdust article)</title><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2021-10-20-squid-game-bridge-problem/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2021-10-20-squid-game-bridge-problem/</guid><description/></item><item><title>generating graphs with community structure via the stochastic block model</title><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2021-09-19-stochastic-block-model/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2021-09-19-stochastic-block-model/</guid><description/></item><item><title>components of a graph and spectrum of its Laplacian matrix</title><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2021-09-08-graph-components/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2021-09-08-graph-components/</guid><description/></item><item><title>diffusion of heat on a graph</title><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2021-08-25-diffusion-on-graphs/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2021-08-25-diffusion-on-graphs/</guid><description/></item><item><title>start-up companies working towards the deployment of MOFs</title><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2021-03-31-mof-startups/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2021-03-31-mof-startups/</guid><description>author: Cory Simon
metal-organic frameworks (MOFs) are (often) crystalline materials that possess nanometer-sized cavities and exhibit large internal surface areas ($&amp;gt;$7000 m$^2$/g) decorable with functional groups. this endows MOFs with the ability to [selectively] adsorb molecules into their pores/ on their internal surfaces. MOFs have many applications; prominent ones are storing, separating, and sensing gases.
MOFs are synthesized modularly from molecular building blocks: organic linker molecules and inorganic nodes. owing to the (i) abundance of compatible molecular building blocks, (ii) many topologies in which the building blocks assemble, and (iii) post-synthetic modifiability, the number of possible MOF structures is practically limitless.</description></item><item><title>the pursuit of science for understanding our natural world</title><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2020-01-03-crispr-book/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2020-01-03-crispr-book/</guid><description>author: Cory Simon
First, I recommend the book &amp;ldquo;A Crack in Creation: gene editing and the unthinkable power to control evolution&amp;rdquo; by the pioneer of the CRISPR-Cas9 genome editing technology, Jennifer Doudna, and her former graduate student, Samuel Sternberg. The book outlines the story of how the CRISPR-Cas9 gene editing technology was developed, discusses its potential to improve human and plant health, and deliberates over ethical questions surrounding its use.</description></item><item><title>cookies and coffees method for counting</title><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2019-11-29-stars-and-bars/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2019-11-29-stars-and-bars/</guid><description>author: Cory Simon
A dog 🐶, bear 🐻, and monkey 🐒 go out to eat together at a restaurant. For desert, the server generously brings five cookies (🍪&amp;rsquo;s). How many different ways can the five cookies be distributed among the three diners? The cookies are indistinguisable.
For example, one outcome is:
🐶: 🍪 🍪
🐻:
🐒: 🍪 🍪 🍪
The answer to this combinatorics problem is readily apparent once cast into the stars and bars framework.</description></item><item><title>the German tank problem</title><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2019-11-15-german-tank-problem/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2019-11-15-german-tank-problem/</guid><description>author: Cory Simon
The German tank problem [1] is intellectually stimulating and makes great conversation at wine bars. The problem has a historical context as well [2].
During World War 2, the Germans inscribed their tanks with sequential serial numbers $1,2,&amp;hellip;,n$ when they were manufactured. The total number of tanks $n$ that the Germans had, however, was unknown to the Allied forces&amp;ndash; and of great interest.
The Allies captured a (assumed) random sample of $k$ tanks from the German forces (without replacement, of course) and observed their serial numbers, $x_1,x_2,&amp;hellip;,x_k$.</description></item><item><title>interactive visualization of a metal-organic cuboctahedron</title><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2019-07-07-mo-cage-viz/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2019-07-07-mo-cage-viz/</guid><description/></item><item><title>dynamic models for liquid flow into/out of tanks with complicated geometries</title><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2019-03-22-tank-problem/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2019-03-22-tank-problem/</guid><description>author: Cory Simon
Problem setup Liquid continuously flows into a truncated square pyramidal tank at a rate $q_i=q_i(t)$ [m$^3$/s]. Hydrostatic pressure drives flow out of the tank through a narrow pipe at its base; via Bernoulli&amp;rsquo;s equation, the outlet flow rate $q\propto \sqrt{h}$, where $h$ [m] is the liquid level in the tank.
The goal here is to derive a dynamic model for the liquid level $h=h(t)$ given any input $q_i(t)$.</description></item><item><title>surface tension catapults in mushrooms</title><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2018-11-28-surface-tension-catapult/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2018-11-28-surface-tension-catapult/</guid><description>author: Cory Simon
Fungi Basidiomycota have evolved a fascinating mechanism by which they discharge their spores. The mechanism exploits surface tension in water, which can be intuited1 as the tendency to minimize surface area.
Here&amp;rsquo;s how it works, aided by a visual pulled from Stolze-Rybczynski et al. [2], who took high-speed videos of these spores launching. The authors [2] dub this a &amp;ldquo;surface tension catapult&amp;rdquo;.
The spore starts off attached to a sterigma.</description></item><item><title>the orthogonal Procrustes problem</title><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2018-10-27-orthogonal-procrustes/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2018-10-27-orthogonal-procrustes/</guid><description>author: Cory Simon
The orthogonal Procrustes problem is to find the orthogonal matrix that maps a given set of points closest to another given set of points; the one-to-one correspondence of points between the two sets must be known a priori. The solution has applications in computer vision, molecular modeling, and speech translation.
The nomenclature refers to a character in Greek mythology, Procrustes, a bandit who stretched or cut off the limbs of his victims to fit his iron bed.</description></item><item><title>Monte Carlo simulation of airline overbooking</title><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2018-07-24-airline-overbooking/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2018-07-24-airline-overbooking/</guid><description>authors: Mira Khare, Melanie Huynh, Arni Sturluson, Cory Simon
Airlines overbook flights to maximize profits.
Consider a flight with seats for 100 passengers.
If the airline allows only up to 100 reservations for the flight, each customer will be guarenteed a seat on the plane. However, several seats will likely be empty because a fraction of the customers that reserve a seat will likely miss the flight. For each empty seat, the airline looses revenue.</description></item><item><title>Monte Carlo simulation of Buffon's Needle</title><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2018-04-11-buffon/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2018-04-11-buffon/</guid><description>authors: Arthur York, Cory Simon
Buffon&amp;rsquo;s Needle is a famous probability problem emanating from the 18th century.
setup Imagine a floor marked with an infinite number of parallel, equidistant lines, a width $\ell$ apart.
We now toss a needle of length $L&amp;lt;\ell$ onto the floor, where it lands at a uniform random position and with a uniform random orientation. Buffon&amp;rsquo;s needle problem is to determine the probability that the needle intersects one of the lines on the floor.</description></item><item><title>the freely jointed chain model</title><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2017-10-6-freelyjointedchain/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/posts/2017-10-6-freelyjointedchain/</guid><description>author: Cory Simon
Single-molecule force spectroscopy is a technique to gauge the binding forces within and mechanical properties of biopolymers. For example, consider a DNA unzipping experiment. At the end of a double-stranded DNA molecule, one strand is tethered to a fixed position, and the other, complementary strand is attached to a microsphere under an optical trap. Then, the two strands are pulled apart, and the force is measured as the hydrogen bonds between base pairs break and the DNA molecule unzips.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/about/</guid><description>hi sup, dude</description></item><item><title/><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/news/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/news/</guid><description>Faaiq will enroll in PhD program in Electrical Engineering at Georgia Tech Faaiq Waqar is officially headed to Georgia Tech in the fall to pursue his PhD in Electrical Engineering! Huge congratulations, Faaiq!
Faaiq, co-advised by Prof. Xiaoli Fern, worked on (i) applying graph neural networks to predict adsorption properties of nanoporous materials and (ii) a tutorial (with heat transfer experiments) on the Bayesian approach to inverse problems.
Nick will intern at Sandia National Labs!</description></item><item><title/><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/pubs/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/pubs/</guid><description>see Google Scholar.
pubs @ Oregon State University "Multi-fidelity Bayesian Optimization of Covalent Organic Frameworks for Xenon/Krypton Separations"
N. Gantzler, A. Deshwal, J. Doppa, C. Simon
ChemRxiv. 2023. link "Data-driven imputation of miscibility of aqueous solutions via graph-regularized logistic matrix factorization"
D. Behnoudfar, C. Simon, J. Schrier
ChemRxiv. 2023. link "A tutorial on the Bayesian statistical approach to inverse problems"
F. Waqar, S. Patel, C. Simon
arXiv. 2023. link "A Bayesian treatment of the German tank problem"</description></item><item><title/><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/students/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/students/</guid><description>phd students Nick Gantzler B.S. Physics, B.S. Applied Mathematics, The University of Akron. research interests: using molecular models and simulations to discover materials for gas separations about: In my free time, I enjoy playing guitar and going to bar trivia. I also really like Japanese media and culture. Some of my favorite animation artists include Hayao Miazaki, Makoto Shinkai, and Satoshi Kon. Adrian Henle B.S. Chemistry, Seattle University. B.S. Computer Science, Oregon State University.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/teaching/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/teaching/</guid><description>teaching Perfection is attained not when there is nothing more to add, but when there is nothing more to remove. &amp;ndash; Antoine de Saint Exupéry courses CHE 361, Process Dynamics and Simulation. (winter quarter)
CHE 461, Process Control. (spring quarter)
CHE 599 (graduate course), Data Science for Engineers. (fall quarter)</description></item><item><title/><link>https://simonensemble.github.io/theprof/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://simonensemble.github.io/theprof/</guid><description>cory simon 👋
assistant professor. Ph.D. Chemical Engineering. UC Berkeley.
hails from a small town in Ohio. learned the ropes of scientific research at the University of Akron, Virginia Tech, Okinawa Institute of Science and Technology, University of British Columbia, Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne, and Altius Institute for Biomedical Sciences. interned in industry at Bridgestone Research (chemical engineering) and Stitch Fix (data science).
lives with his girlfriend, Christina, near the research forest, for long walks with his Samoyeds, Oslo and Mochi.</description></item></channel></rss>